<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ios | Kyle Rogers]]></title>
  <link href="http://keroger2k.github.io/blog/categories/ios/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://keroger2k.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-29T21:38:23-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://keroger2k.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kyle Rogers]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Migrating from iOS to Android]]></title>
    <link href="http://keroger2k.github.io/blog/2014/03/29/migrating-from-ios-to-android/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-29T21:15:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://keroger2k.github.io/blog/2014/03/29/migrating-from-ios-to-android</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the past 5 years or so of my life I have had an iPhone in my pocket.  I have really enjoyed the experience for the most part and in the time leading up to this year, even the thought changing made me very uneasy.  I know it is just a phone, but there is something inside me that says it is more.  It seems like it is almost an extension of me.  It helps me with so many aspects of my life that trusting another phone or phone type with that responsibility is very traumatic.</p>

<p>The main reason I made the decision to switch from iOS to Android was the interaction between Apple and Google.  Google’s software for the most part is on almost all platforms.  You can use it or not use.  Apple on the other hand keeps their ecosystem closed and doesn’t allow others to play in their park.  I find it annoying that I can’t make Chrome my default browser in iOS.  I find it annoying that people using Android devices can’t participate in ‘Find My Friends’ or ‘iMessage’.  I find it annoying that when I click on navigation link in Safari, Twitter or Facebook it opens up in Apple Maps and not Google Maps.  There are no ways to change these default behaviors either.  Overall I’m just disappointed in the software.  Hardware is great, but honestly that just isn’t enough for me anymore.</p>

<p>Switching hasn’t been easy.  I’ve had struggles with things, like instant messaging, my new camera, etc…  Every time I struggle I’m not only getting frustrated personally, but I have my loving wife leaning over my shoulder saying, “that phone sucks” or “should have stayed with an iPhone”.  It is very annoying and I will say it hasn’t gone as smoothly as I had hoped.</p>

<p>So if you are like me and have recently migrated from iOS to the Android ecosystem or maybe you are considering the change, perhaps you might want to read on and hear about my experience.</p>

<p>I’m going to break this post into three main parts.  Things you need to know and do once you have changed.  Things that I like and obviously things that I don’t.</p>

<h2>What you need to know</h2>

<h3>iMessage</h3>

<p>First and the biggest hurdle I had to deal with was iMessage.  It was a huge pain to get my messaging straight with all my friends.  Here are the three steps I took to get my iMessage service disabled and back to being able to communicate with my friends and family either via SMS or messaging.</p>

<p>-Going to the <a href="https://supportprofile.apple.com/">apple support site</a> and removing my device from the device list.  I still have a couple apple devices so I just removed my phone.
-On my iPad and my Macbook Pro I completely disabled iMessaging.  You might still be able to use your Apple Id for messaging but it just seemed to complicate things in my scenario.<br/>
-Text ‘stop’ to the number ‘48369’.  You should get a response similar to: “FREE MSG: Apple iCloud ID Verification: You have been unsubscribed and will no longer receive messages.”</p>

<h3>Hangouts</h3>

<p>Now that you have iMessaging completely disabled you need to have a way to communicate with others.  The best solution I have found for this is <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.google.android.talk">Hangouts</a>.  Hangouts has support for both iOS and Android platforms.</p>

<p>Finding people who use hangouts on iOS is not quite as easy, but they do exist.  In fact as of writing this iOS hangouts just got a very nice update and I would say the iOS version of hangouts is better than the Android version.  Go figure.  Hangouts allows you to message over your internet connection in Android and it also allows you to use SMS.  The unfortunate thing is you have to manually select your option.  Where Apple abstracts that responsibility from you, with hangouts you have to either choose the email address or the phone number.  This is mildly annoying.  I would think this is something the android market would be rectifying sooner than later to keep the messaging system as simple as possible.  Hangouts has the potential to be a very nice messaging platform and Google has all the technology required to make it amazing.  They just need to figure out a way to bring it all together in one application on all platforms.</p>

<h3>Find My Friends</h3>

<p>Another Apple proprietary application.  This has been another hurdle to jump in my migration but I think I have found the solution.  I use Google+ for managing my photos and for a more technical social network than Facebook.  Google+ allows you to track your location and so far my wife and I have been using Google+ for this feature.  There are quite a few other options out there that are supported on both iOS and Android, but I have yet to use any of them.</p>

<h2>Things I like</h2>

<h3>Google Integration</h3>

<p>When I set up the phone I sign in with my Google account and that is the last time I had to login.  The one negative aspect of this experience is the fact that I use ‘Two-Factor Authentication’ and I was unable to get my text initially to input my verification code.  I resolved this issue by using one of my backup phrases to get the phone initialized.  This might also have been partly to blame on not having disassociated my number with iMessage yet.</p>

<h3>Google Now</h3>

<p>Google Now has been amazing.  It is very well done and seems to understand my voice even in loud settings.  It also tries to predict my life a bit and help me makes decisions.  Google Now seems to know where I’m heading based on searches I’ve made, emails I’ve received, etc.  It also tries to help me find things to do and keep me updated on things that are important to me.  I always get information about my stocks, sports teams and the weather in the place I’m currently located and if I’m going somewhere soon, that location as well.  A lot of this functionality is available on iOS, however it isn’t as easy to access and because of that I seemed to use it quite a bit less.</p>

<h3>Back button</h3>

<p>Something so simple.  The back button.  This button has made navigation so much easier.  I find myself clicking on links that open Chrome, Instagram or Twitter and I can easily just push the back button and be right back where I was without any effort.  The multitask button I find to be quite useful as well.  I know iOS you can double click the home button to present all your applications that are open, but I can’t tell you how many times it hasn’t worked for me the first time and I’ve had to try again.  The multitasking button works every time and I find myself switching between applications with this function quite a bit.</p>

<h3>Swype</h3>

<p>I definitely haven’t mastered this technology yet, but I can definitely feel the potential.  I love how inaccurate you can be and the predictive algorithms still understand what I’m trying to type.  Plus it has the ability to plug into your social life and correlate names and emails in a manor that greatly assists you with texting.  I love that I no longer have to type my usernames and emails because it always remembers them for me.  This application needs to be on all devices, not just android.</p>

<h3>Play Store</h3>

<p>This was the most surprising aspect of my conversion.  I couldn’t believe how social the play store is in comparison to iTunes.  Unfortunately I don’t have a lot of friends that use this store, but for those that do, it is nice to see what applications they like and use their input when deciding on applications myself.</p>

<h3>More Control</h3>

<p>If I don’t want Chrome as the default browser I can change it. If I don’t like the default launcher I can change it.  There are so many things I can customize with this phone it is almost overwhelming.  I can definitely see good and bad in this ability, but for myself I love this aspect.  If I had a bit more creativity in my blood I would take advantage of this more.  On my Google+ feed there are people who post their current setup for the android device and some of the are ridiculously amazing.</p>

<h3>Installing APK’s</h3>

<p>This is something you just can’t do out of the box with an iOS device.  I can find an APK of an application I want to install and just put it on my phone and install it.  I am not required to go through the play store.  I have yet to try this with any other applications than ‘flappy bird’ and the google launcher that comes default with Nexus devices.</p>

<h2>Things I dislike</h2>

<h3>Camera</h3>

<p>Perhaps this is just my phone.  Perhaps it has something to do with Android itself.  I have yet to figure it out.  This is by far the most disappointing aspect of my new phone.  The quality of videos and photos that I’m producing are no where near where my iPhone 4s could produce let alone the new iPhone 5 or above.  I know everyone loves their Android phones and their respective cameras, but so far I have yet to see one that will compete with an iPhone.  I’m not talking about a book or a coffee mug picture where the object is stationary and in low or ideal lighting.  I’m talking about a trouble making kid that is running through a store doing something funny in low light or even normal light and you have very little time to capture the moment.  The pictures are passable.  The ones that are in focus you can usually put an instagram filter on top of it and no one will ever know.  The video isn’t quite as easy to hide.  There are things you can do, but I never used to have to do any of this in the past.  With the most recent update of Android 4.4.2 Kitkat I have seen some improvement, but it still is disappointing.</p>

<h3>Messaging</h3>

<p>This is such a huge part of my life and since moving to android it just hasn’t been as easy.  I would say 95% of my friends have iPhone’s so using iMessage was a very common situation.  Now that I don’t have this option I can’t easily communicate with my friends on my computer like I could with iMessage.  Hangouts has this option, but it doesn’t matter because very few people have hangouts on their iOS devices and you can’t SMS with hangouts.  There is a chrome extension called <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/motorola-connect/kigmoblgooahdmdibodmcnffgnejlndh?hl=en">motorola connect</a> that lets you text via your browser which will suffice until something more elegant comes along.</p>

<h3>Updates</h3>

<p>I’m not a fan of Verizon getting an update before AT&amp;T or vice versa.  I find it really annoying to look at blog posts and photos of people showing off features or improvements of their phones that I’m not able to do because my carrier hasn’t updated my phone as of yet.  This isn’t a huge issue, but I still don’t have to like it.</p>

<h3>Screen interactions</h3>

<p>I’m finding that android doesn’t seem as accurate as my iOS device.  I don’t know if iOS does some decision making for me or something, but when I click on keys or links with Android I seem to miss a lot more often.  I also find that I get more actions that don’t produce any sort of response.  I think we always get things like this that happen no matter what type of device we use, but it just seems to happen a bit more on my android device.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Overall, I’m very happy I made the jump.  I just took a trip to Chicago where I was using it for directions and locations constantly and it worked amazing.  The voice activation features that come with the phone are sort of a gimmick, but they do have their uses.  Not the uses you see in the commercial, but I do use them for calling people when I’m driving without having to take my focus off the road.</p>

<p>Android is an amazing product. I am very excited about heading down this new road with Google and whoever else decides to tag along.  Open source has a great community around it.  Everyone is excited to share their products with you.  Now if I can just get this damn camera issue fixed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
